Finding Aid for R. W. Fleming papers, 1920-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
R. W. Fleming papers 1920-2010
Fleming, R.W. (Robben Wright), 1916-
85232 Aa 2; UAm
Ninth president of the University of Michigan, 1967-1978, later president of the Corporation for Public Broadcasting, chairman of the National Institute for Dispute Resolution, and member of the boards of the MacArthur and Johnson Foundations. Personal files, including general and family correspondence, papers detailing service with the U. S. Army military police in Europe during World War II, records concerning activities as labor arbitrator, topical files relating to work at universities of Illinois, Wisconsin, and Michigan; files relating to activities with the Corporation for Public Broadcasting concerning in part the Annenberg/CPB project; and photographs relating to his life and career.
51 linear feet in 52 boxes
1 oversize folders
5.9 GB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 5769 ) was the gift of Robben Fleming in 1979. Periodic additions have been received since 1979.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
Robben Fleming was born in Paw Paw, Illinois, on December 18, 1916. He was active in student affairs and athletics throughout his student life. Fleming received his Bachelor of Arts degree in 1938 from Beloit College and went on to the University of Wisconsin where he received his LL.B. in 1941.
Soon after his graduation from Wisconsin, Fleming went to Washington, D.C. to work for the Reorganization Division of the Securities and Exchange Commission as a junior attorney. In April 1942, Fleming began working for the National War Labor Board, where he dealt with labor relations and wage control. That same month Fleming married Aldyth (Sally) Quixley, whom he had met while both were students at Beloit College. Fleming was inducted into the United States Army in October 1942.
After induction into the army, Fleming was sent to Fort Riley, Kansas to receive basic training. On January 16, 1943, Fleming arrived at Fort Custer, Michigan where he remained until May 1943, enrolled first in the Military Police Officer Candidate School, and later in the Occupational Police School. Here, Fleming was trained for service as a civil affairs officer in Military Government. Following close on the heels of the combat forces, the Military Government units were responsible for restoring order and establishing effective government in occupied territories.
In August 1943, having completed his training, Fleming, now a 2nd lieutenant, was sent to Italy along with other Military Government personnel to gain practical experience in administering occupied territories. Fleming remained in Italy only a few months before being transferred to England in preparation for the Allied invasion of Europe. Fleming's active military career began in October 1944. His unit was responsible for severing active Nazi party members from local government, housing and feeding displaced persons, organizing transportation for food delivery to the cities, and returning stability to local affairs and government. As a civil affairs officer, Fleming put his civilian training in law and labor relations to good use, supervising civilian labor agencies and services, providing liaison between these agencies and the military government, establishing wage scales and controls, and acting as legal officer, serving at various times as judge, prosecutor, and defense counsel in civil affairs trials. Fleming served in Luxembourg, and the German cities of Stolberg, Haltern, Uebach, Soligen, Mallersdorf, and Landshut, with the American 9th and 1st Armies.
Following his discharge from the army in March 1946, Fleming returned to Washington where he found a position as a labor specialist with the National Emergency Housing Program. In July 1947, Fleming was appointed director of the University of Wisconsin Industrial Relations Center. In 1952, he moved to the University of Illinois where he accepted a similar position, becoming director of the Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations. In 1958, Fleming was appointed professor of law at that university. From 1964 to 1967, Fleming served as provost, later chancellor, and professor of law at the University of Wisconsin's Madison campus. Throughout this period, 1948-1967, Fleming arbitrated numerous grievances between labor unions and various private companies.
Robben Fleming was inaugurated as the ninth president of the University of Michigan on March 11, 1968. He had been involved throughout his career in arbitration and education, which made Fleming ideally suited to head a major educational institution during the era of student unrest and institutional upheaval which followed. During Fleming's tenure, the Ann Arbor campus was rocked by a number of strikes and disturbances in which Fleming's abilities proved invaluable. These disturbances included the Black Action Movement (BAM) strike in March 1970, the AFSCME (American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees) strike in January 1971, the Graduate Employees Association (GEO) strike, which lasted from February 11 to March 14, 1975, and the second AFSCME strike which lasted from February 23 to March 20, 1977.
In 1978 Fleming retired as president, and in 1979 he became the president of the Corporation for Public Broadcasting. In 1981 he returned to the University of Michigan as a part-time professor of law and educational consultant for such projects as the Annenberg Project for the Corporation for Public Broadcasting, the Kellogg Foundation and the National Institute for Dispute Resolution.
In 1985 Fleming was appointed by Governor Blanchard to chair a committee to study medical malpractice insurance problems in Michigan. Fleming wrote a draft report in December 1985. A series of tort reform bills were passed in 1986, and Fleming submitted an analysis of these to the governor.
The Board of Regents appointed Robben Fleming interim president of the University of Michigan in 1988 following the resignation of Harold Shapiro. In this capacity he served from January 1988 through August 1988. During his second tenure as president, Fleming once again had to address questions pertaining to racism on campus that were raised by such groups as the United Coalition Against Racism (UCAR).
In the years after Fleming's retirement from the University of Michigan he continued to do part-time consulting work for various organizations. In 1988 Fleming was re-appointed by Governor Blanchard to study medical malpractice. Fleming reported to the governor on alternative adjudicatory procedures as well as on ways to reduce the incidence of malpractice.
The Robben Fleming collection documents a career marked by diversity in the areas of his public service. The cornerstone of his life is no doubt his years as ninth president of The University of Michigan. While this role is certainly documented in these papers, there is considerable other materials relating to his service in World War II, his work as a labor arbitrator and law professor, his work with the Corporation for Public Broadcasting, and his advocacy in other arenas of the importance of higher education. As Fleming worked in various educational and corporate settings, the records of that service properly belonged to those agencies. This collection, by and large, consists of personal materials retained by Fleming or copies of records given to Fleming as his own. Thus, for example, while this collection includes speeches, invitations, and personal correspondence, maintained while he was President of The University of Michigan, the records of the Office of the President for Fleming's tenure have been received and cataloged separately. Even so, the content of these materials is highly valuable on any number of topics, but specifically higher education broadly defined.
The series in the collection are Correspondence; World War II service; School materials; Labor Arbitration files; Career Activities to 1967; University of Michigan President, 1967-1978; Corporation for Public Broadcasting; Other Organizational Activities; Topical Files, 1978-2000; Knight v. State of Alabama; Publications, speeches, and reports; Personal and Autobiographical Materials; Travel Records; Clippings and Scrapbooks; Photographs; and Other visual and audio materials.
Subjects:
Arbitration, Industrial.; Annenberg/CPB Project.; Corporation for Public Broadcasting.; Fleming, R. W. (Robben Wright), 1916-2010.; Fleming, Sally.; John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation.; Johnson Foundation (Racine, Wis.); National Institute for Dispute Resolution (U.S.); United States. Army. Corps of Military Police.; University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign campus); University of Michigan--History.; University of Michigan. President.; University of Wisconsin.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Athletics.; Birthdays.; Children.; China--History--1949-; Costumes.; Europe.; Families.; Fleming family.; Fleming, Sally.; Fleming, R. W. (Robben Wright), 1916-2010.; Leisure.; Living rooms--1961-1970.; Military uniforms--United States.; Music.; Quixley family.; Weddings.; Wisconsin.; United States. Army.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Paintings.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  Correspondence consists of general correspondence with friends and colleagues; family correspondence, primarily letters between Robben and Sally and their children, ca. 1950-1990, and letters of congratulations and regrets. There is finally the letters from Robben Fleming to his wife and to other family members while serving in World War II. This includes both regular mail and V-mail [letters photocopied and reduced by the Army for easier transmission home to the states].
  - General correspondence
    - Undated 1920s-1943 (Box 1)
    - 1944-1982 (Box 2)
    - 1983-1990 (Box 3)
    - 1991-2001 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, outgoing 1982-1985, 17 folders (Box 5)
  - Universities--personal correspondence 1977-1981, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Fleming Family Correspondence
    - Undated and miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1964 (Box 5)
    - 1965 (Box 5)
    - circa 1965-1966 (Nancy Fleming, University of Beirut), 3 folders (Box 5)
    - December 1965-February 1966 (Nancy Fleming, University of Beirut) (Box 5)
    - March-June 1966 (Nancy Fleming, University of Beirut) (Box 5)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 5)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 5)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 5)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - 1976 and undated circa 1976/1977 (Box 5)
    - 1977 and undated circa 1977/1978 (Box 5)
    - 1978 (Box 5)
    - 1982-1986 (Box 6)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 6)
    - Wedding and graduation announcements (Box 6)
    - Fleming Christmas letters and cards 1950-1980, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Letters of congratulations, regrets, etc.
    - Letters of recommendation for Robben Fleming 1941-1957
      - Related materials (Box 6)
    - Letters of congratulations on Fleming's appointment as University of Wisconsin Provost and Professor of Law 1964, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Letters of congratulations on Fleming's appointment as President of the University of Michigan 1967 (arranged alphabetically), 18 folders (Box 6)
    - Letters of regret on Fleming's departure from the University of Michigan
      - September 1978 1978 undated (Box 6)
      - October-December 1978 (Box 6)
      - December 1978 (include Christmas cards with notes), 3 folders (Box 6)
  - World War II correspondence
    - Letters from Robben Fleming to Sally Fleming, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - V-Mail September 1943-September 1945
      - September 1943-July 1944 (Box 8)
      - August 1944-September 1945 (Box 8)
- World War II service
  The series relating to Fleming's service in World War II is rich, and includes diaries and a manuscript titled G.I. Government, written by Fleming shortly after the war and detailing his wartime experiences.
  - Diaries August 1943-December 1945, 3 volumes (Box 8)
  - G.I. Government (manuscript by R.W. Fleming; 257 pp.) (Box 8)
  - G.I. Government (partial draft) (Box 8)
  - Personnel records 1943-1946 (Box 8)
  - Drafts of correspondence (Box 8)
  - Case materials, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Landshut, photo book on Landshut, Germany (Box 8)
- School materials
  The School Materials series is small and concerns his education at Beloit College before the war.
  - Pre-college (miscellaneous notes and assignments) (Box 9)
  - Beloit College
    - Course book 1938 and miscellaneous Beloit publications, circa 1937, 1939 (Box 9)
    - "The Round Table", Beloit College Newspaper 1934-1938 Yearbooks, 1935-1938, 3 volumes (Box 9)
- Labor Arbitration files
  The Labor Arbitration files contain materials relating to Fleming's career as an arbitrator. This series includes a possibly complete run of his grievance opinions [the judgment rendered by the arbitrator(s) after an arbitration hearing has been held], 1948-1967, and a sample of Fleming's arbitration case files, several of which are complete, containing briefs, exhibits, and correspondence.
  - Grievance Opinions 1948-1951, 23 folders (Box 9)
  - Case records (including correspondence and briefs)
    - New York Shipping Association AND The International Longshoremen's Association 1962 (Box 9)
    - Central Greyhound Lines AND Division 1313 Amalgamated Association of Street, Electric Railway and Motor Coach Employees of America, AFL-CIO [hereafter referred to as "AAS"] 1963 (Box 10)
    - Central Greyhound Lines AND Division 1150 AAS 1963 (Box 10)
    - Eastern Greyhound Lines AND Division 1205 AAS 1963 (Box 10)
    - Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company AND the United Glass and Ceramic Workers of North America, AFL-CIO-CLC 1963 (Box 10)
    - Communications Workers of America AND Southwestern Bell Telephone Company 1965 (Box 10)
    - Southern Greyhound Lines AND Division 1315 AAS 1965 (Box 10)
    - Eastern Greyhound Lines AND Division 1210 Amalgamated Transit Union 1965 (Box 10)
    - United Steelworkers of America AND Thermo King Corporation 1965 (Box 10)
    - The Goss Co. of Rockford, Ill. AND Unity Lodge No. 1553 International Association of Machinists, AFL-CIO 1966 (Box 10)
    - A.P. Green Refractories AND United Birch and Clay Workers of America, Local 790 1966 (Box 10)
    - Southern Bell Telephone and Telegraph Co. AND Communications Workers of America, AFL-CIO 1966 (Box 10)
    - Indianapolis Launderers and Cleaners Club AND Local 3017 Laundry and Dry Cleaning International Union 1966
      - Correspondence 1965-1967 (Box 10)
      - Exhibits, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - United States Steel Corporation, South Works AND Salaried Employees Association
      - Briefs and correspondence (Box 10)
      - Hearing transcript (Box 10)
      - Exhibits (Box 10)
    - Southern Greyhound Lines AND "Union" 1967 (Box 10)
  - Topical files
    - First National Labor Arbitration Conference June 10-12, 1965 Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 10)
    - Indian Academy of Labor Arbitrators 1966-1967 (Box 10)
    - Minutes of Panel Discussions on Arbitration 1958 (Box 10)
    - National Academy of Arbitrators
      - Correspondence 1965-1966 (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Polygraph Use Arbitration (source materials) (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
- Career Activities to 1967
  Fleming' activities prior to coming to the University of Michigan are documented in the Career Activities (prior to 1967) series. The bulk of these material concern his years at the University of Wisconsin.
  - Labor Advisory Service Personnel Files 1946-1948 (Box 11)
  - The University of Wisconsin
    - Industrial Relations Center Report 1947-1952 (draft copy) (Box 11)
    - Reports and miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - News releases and related materials 1948-1952 (Box 11)
    - Report of the Special Committee to Consider Resolution of Board of Regents concerning Labor Management Problems February 15, 1947 (Box 11)
    - College of Law (faculty minutes) 1958-1959 (Box 11)
    - "The Wisconsin Badger" 1965-1967 ("Administration" section only) (Box 11)
    - Student Demonstration Against Dow Chemical Company 1967-1968 (Box 11)
      (correspondence regarding Fleming's furnishing of bail money for arrested students)
    - Miscellaneous 1967-1968 with some earlier material (Box 11)
  - U.A.W. Public Review Board
    - 1966 (Box 11)
    - 1967 1969 (Box 11)
  - The University of Illinois
    - Executive Visit 1960 to the Uttar Pradesh, Agricultural University, India 1957-1964 (report, notes, and source materials) (Box 11)
- University of Michigan President 1967-1978
  The University of Michigan President series includes personal files received from the President's House and from the President's Office. Within this series are personal communications, invitations accepted, speeches given as President, and records from his foreign travels representing the University of Michigan.
  - Materials from the President's House
    - Report on the selection of a president 1967 (Box 11)
    - Fleming Inauguration 1967 (includes program, guest list, and copy of Fleming address) (Box 11)
    - President's home 1967-1968 (includes history and notes on activities) (Box 11)
    - Fleming resignation 1978 (comments upon) (Box 11)
    - Presidential dinner 1979 (program, notes of Regent Sarah Power, remarks, correspondence) (Box 11)
    - Student unrest 1968-1969 (includes correspondence, publications and memoranda) (Box 11)
  - Personal Papers from president's office
    - Biographical and bibliographical materials (Box 12)
    - Arbitration (Box 12)
    - Articles
      - 1967-1972 (Box 12)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 12)
      - 1975-1978 (Box 12)
    - Awards and honorary degrees (Box 12)
    - Bibliography worksheets (Box 12)
    - Book Reviews (Box 12)
    - Chrysler Corporation: fees and deposits (Box 12)
    - Corporation for Public Broadcasting
      - Congratulations on appointment, 6 folders (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
    - Correspondence
      - 1967-1968
        - Accolades/appreciations/criticisms (Box 12)
        - Book materials: humor (Box 13)
        - Committees (Box 13)
        - Condolence letters (Box 13)
        - Friends (Box 13)
        - Issues (Box 13)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
        - Newell, Barbara W. (Box 13)
        - Professional
          - Arbitration Seminar (Box 13)
          - General (Box 13)
          - Labor Law Seminar (Box 13)
          - National Mediation Board (Box 13)
        - Recommendations (Box 13)
        - Speeches and statements (Box 13)
      - 1968-1969
        - Accolades/appreciations/criticisms (Box 13)
        - Acknowledgments (Box 13)
        - Book materials: humor (Box 13)
        - Committees (Box 13)
        - Condolences (Box 13)
        - Friends (Box 13)
        - Issues (Box 13)
        - Kauffman, Joseph (Box 13)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
        - Professional
          - General (Box 13)
          - Labor Law Seminar (Box 13)
          - National Academy of Arbitrators (Box 13)
          - National Labor Relations Board (Box 13)
        - Recommendations (Box 13)
        - Speeches and statements (Box 13)
        - Television (NBC) August 16, 1968 (Box 13)
        - Wisconsin, University of (Box 13)
      - 1969-1970
        - Accolades/appreciations/criticisms (Box 13)
        - Acknowledgments (Box 13)
        - Book materials: humor (Box 13)
        - Friends (Box 13)
        - Issues (Box 13)
        - Professional
          - General (Box 13)
          - Labor Law Seminar (Box 13)
        - Recommendations (Box 13)
        - Speeches--statements (Box 13)
      - 1970-1971
        - Accolades/appreciations/criticism (Box 13)
        - Acknowledgments (Box 13)
        - Book materials: humor (Box 13)
        - Committees (Box 13)
        - Condolence letters (Box 14)
        - Friends (Box 14)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
        - Professional
          - General (Box 14)
          - Labor Law Seminar (Box 14)
        - Recommendations (Box 14)
        - Speeches and statements (Box 14)
      - 1971-1972
        - Accolades/appreciations/criticism (Box 14)
        - Acknowledgments (Box 14)
        - Book materials: humor (Box 14)
        - Carnegie Corporation Conference on Collective Bargaining (Box 14)
        - Friends (Box 14)
        - Issues (Box 14)
        - Miscellaneous
          - Professional Labor Law Seminar (Box 14)
          - National Academy of Arbitrators (Box 14)
        - Recommendations (Box 14)
        - Speeches and statements (Box 14)
      - 1972-1973
        - Accolades/appreciations/criticism (Box 14)
        - Acknowledgments (Box 14)
        - Book materials: humor (Box 14)
        - Committees (Box 14)
        - Condolence letters (Box 14)
        - Friends (Box 14)
        - Newell, Barbara W. (Box 14)
        - Recommendations (Box 14)
        - Speeches and statements (Box 14)
        - Travel: leaves of absence (Box 14)
        - Wisconsin State Journal (editorial and reply) (Box 14)
      - 1973-1974
        - Accolades/appreciations/criticism (Box 14)
        - Book materials: humor (Box 14)
        - Committees (Box 14)
        - Condolence letters (Box 14)
        - Friends (Box 14)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
        - Recommendations (Box 14)
        - Speeches and statements (Box 14)
      - 1974-1975
        - Accolades/appreciations/criticism (Box 14)
        - Acknowledgments (Box 14)
        - Book materials: humor (Box 14)
        - Committees (Box 14)
        - Condolence letters (Box 14)
        - Friends (Box 14)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
        - Professional
          - General (Box 14)
          - Labor Law (Box 14)
          - Labor Law Seminar (Box 14)
        - Recommendations (Box 14)
        - Speeches and statements (Box 14)
      - 1975-1976
        - Accolades/appreciations/criticism (Box 14)
        - Acknowledgments (Box 14)
        - Book materials: humor (Box 14)
        - Committees (Box 14)
        - Condolence letters (Box 14)
        - Friends (Box 14)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
        - Professional: general (Box 14)
        - Recommendations (Box 14)
        - Retirement plans (Box 14)
        - Speeches and statements (Box 14)
        - Travel: leaves of absence (Box 14)
        - Wisconsin, University of (Box 14)
      - 1976-1977
        - Accolades/appreciations/criticism (Box 14)
        - Acknowledgments (Box 14)
        - Book materials: humor (Box 14)
        - Committees (Box 14)
        - Condolence letters (Box 15)
        - Friends (Box 15)
        - Issues (Box 15)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
        - Professional: general (Box 15)
        - Recommendations (Box 15)
        - Retirement plans (Box 15)
        - Speeches and statements (Box 15)
        - Travel: leaves of absence (Box 15)
      - 1977-1978
        - Accolades/appreciations/criticism (Box 15)
        - Acknowledgments (Box 15)
        - Book materials: humor (Box 15)
        - Committees (Box 15)
        - Condolence letters (Box 15)
        - Friends (Box 15)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
        - Professional: general (Box 15)
        - Recommendations (Box 15)
        - Retirement plans (Box 15)
        - Speeches and statements (Box 15)